A Finding Aid to the Henry G. Keller Papers, circa 1880-1962, in the Archives of American Art aaa.kellhenr
Archives of American Art
Henry G. Keller papers
circa 1880-1962
aaa.kellhenr
Archives of American Art
1.3 Linear feet
The papers of Ohio painter, lithographer, and educator Henry G. Keller date from circa 1880-1962 and measure 1.3 linear feet. Found are biographical materials, professional and personal correspondence, writings and notes, personal business records, printed material, photographs, and artworks and artifacts.
Arrangement note
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1920-1945 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1905-1961 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1920-circa 1952 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, circa 1925-circa 1955 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1913-1962 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1880-circa 1940 (0.3 linear feet; Box 2, 4)
Series 7: Sketchbooks, Artwork and Artifacts, circa 1898-1948 (0.4 linear feet; Box 2-4)
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Biographical/Historical note
Henry G. Keller (1869-1949) was a painter, lithographer, and educator active in Cleveland, Ohio.
In 1869, Henry Keller was born at sea to German parents who settled in Northern Ohio. Keller received arts education in Cleveland as well as the Academy of Fine Arts, Karlsruhem, Germany and the Art Students League in New York City. He returned to Ohio where he worked as a lithographer for the Morgan Lithography Company. For forty years, Keller taught painting classes at the Cleveland School of Art (Cleveland Institute of Art) and at his artist colony in Berlin Heights, Ohio.
Keller married Imogene Leslie in 1893 and they had two sons, Albert and Leslie. The family travelled throughout Europe. After the death of his wife, Henry Keller moved to California to be with Albert. He died a year later in 1949.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Henry G. Keller papers were donated by Albert Keller via the Cleveland Museum of Art in 1976.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Ohio painter, lithographer, and educator Henry G. Keller date from circa 1880-1962 and measure 1.3 linear feet. Found are biographical materials, professional and personal correspondence, writings and notes, personal business records, printed material, photographs, and artworks and artifacts.
The bulk of Henry Keller's correspondence relates to the sale and exhibition of his works of art. Letters are found from institution and museums including the Carnegie Institute and the Cleveland Museum of Art. Also, correspondence is found for Albert Keller, most of which concerns his father's career and estate.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The papers are also available on microfilm reel 1321. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan but researchers are advised that the microfilm does not reflect the current order of the papers.
Carnegie Institute; Cleveland Museum of Art; Keller, Albert; Keller, Henry G., 1869-1949; Lithographers--Ohio--Cleveland; Painters--Ohio--Cleveland; Photographs
- Biographical Material, circa 1920-1945; Series 1; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found is a biographical sketch, invitations and programs for events, two Keller family Christmas cards, and a ticket to the Alhambra.
  - Biographical Sketch, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Invitations and Programs, 1937-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Keller Family Holiday Cards, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Travel Souvenirs, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1905-1961; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Found is correspondence for Henry Keller, Imogene Keller, Albert Keller, and letters by others relating to the Cleveland Museum of Art.
  Henry Keller correspondence includes personal and professional correspondence, mostly relating to the sale and exhibition of his works at various institutions. Institutions and museums fouund include: Art Institute of Chicago, Brooklyn Museum, Carnegie Institute, Cleveland Museum of Art, Dallas Musuem of the Fine Arts, Fogg Art Museum, Museum of Fine Arts Boston, Museum of Modern Art, New York Public Library, Toledo Museum of Art, Whitney Museum, and Worcester Art Museum.
  Imogene Keller correspondence consists of postcards and letters from family and friends.
  Albert Keller correspondence relates to his father's art and memorial exibitions.
  There are several letters to William Milliken and Louise Dunn of the Cleveland Museum of Art from Jacob Burke and David Hills. Some letters mention Henry Keller's art.
  - Henry Keller Correspondence, 1905-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Imogene Leslie Keller Correspondence, 1905-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Albert Keller Correspondence, 1931-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family Postcards, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Other Correspondence, 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Letters are to Louise Dunn and William Milliken of the Cleveland Museum of Art, from David Hills and Jacob Burke.
- Writings and Notes, circa 1920-circa 1952; Series 3; 4 Folders Box 1
  Found are scattered writings and notes by Henry Keller including: a typescript of a speech given at the Buckeye Art Club, poetry, and notes. Also found is a writing about fiberglass by Albert Keller.
  - Speech, by Keller, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Poetry, Likely by Keller, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notes, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - on Fiberglass, by Albert Keller, circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1925-circa 1955; Series 4; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Found are scattered materials of the sale, consignment, loan, and gift of Henry Keller's art, and estate papers. Also found are records from Albert Keller including personal receipts and material relating to his company, San Luco, Inc..
  - Price Lists, circa 1925-circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gift Acknowledgements, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sales, Consignment, and Loan Records, 1928-1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Receipts, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Estate Papers, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Albert Keller Financial Records, 1951-circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
- Printed Material, 1913-1962; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Found are materials relating to Henry Kellers art and teaching career. Included are: published material; exhibtion announcements and catalogs for solo and group shows; clippings from magazines and newspapers; an advertisement for Keller's sketch class taught at his school in Berlin Heights, Ohio; and blank postcards and a greeting card.
  - The Application of the Philosophy of Color Vision in Modern Art, by Henry Keller and J. J. R. MacCleod, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1915-1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, 1915-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Advertisement for Sketch Class, circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Blank Postcards and Greeting Cards, 1901-circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photographs, circa 1880-circa 1940; Series 6; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2, 4
  Found are photographs of the Keller family, Keller's studio, travel photos, animals, and of exhibitions at the Carnegie Institute and the Cleveland Museum of Art. The family photos were likely taken throughout Cleveland, Lakewood, and Berlin Heights, Ohio. Many of the photographs are unidenfied. Also found are photos of works of art by Keller and others.
  - Portraits of Henry Keller, circa 1910-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Snapshot of Henry Keller, circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Henry Keller painting outside, likely along Lake Erie
  - Snapshots of Keller Family, circa 1880-circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Group Photos, circa 1890-circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Unidentified, likely includes Keller
  - Unidentified Portraits and Snapshots, circa 1900-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Likely of Keller family and friends
  - Studio, Berlin Heights (?), circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Snapshots of Landscapes, circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Wade Park Lagoon and Lake Erie
  - Travel Photos, circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Animals, circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Exhibitions, circa 1935-1944 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Includes photos from the Carnegie Institute and the Cleveland Museum of Art. Oversized material housed in Box 4.
  - Works of Art by Keller, circa 1920-circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Works of Art by Others, circa 1930-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - Oversized Exhibition Photos from Box 2, F16, circa 1935 (Box 4)
- Sketchbooks, Artwork and Artifacts, circa 1898-1948; Series 7; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2-4
  Found are 7 sketchbooks and a loose sketch by Henry Keller, a print by Reindel, and artifacts. Most of the sketchbooks contain pencil sketches and are of faces, figures, and animals. Some of the sketchbooks may have been used during Keller's trips abroad.
  - Sketch, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Sketchbook 1, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sketchbooks 2-7, circa 1898-circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Etching by Reindel, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Artifacts, circa 1900-circa 1945 (Box 4)
    Includes a commemorative medal of the 125th anniversary of the founding of the city of Cleveland, eye glasses, paint brushes and lithography tools, and other items.